A Guide to the Merrill W. Chase papers, Rockefeller University Faculty FA150
Rockefeller Archive Center
Merrill W. Chase papers, Rockefeller University Faculty
1966-1972
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University
Chase, Merrill W.
FA150
5 Cubic Feet 6 boxes and 2 packages. Extent is approximate.
6 boxes and 2 packages.
File Plan note
Former Classifiction: I 450 C386
Conditions Governing Access note
This collection is open for scholarly research, with select materials restricted as noted.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
Cell and biomolecular sciences; Immunology; Epidemics; Medicine, Preventive; Epidemiology; Operations management; Medical education; Medical research; Medical sciences; Rockefeller University; Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research; Chase, Merrill W.
- 1966-1971, 1 box and 1 oversize package
  Scope and Contents
  Conference material, manuscripts, notices and memoranda, posters, printed matter, slides, correspondence, minutes, manuscripts, report, drafts, laboratory notes, clippings and reprints.
  Box 1 consists primarily of materials collected or photographed by Dr. Chase during the student unrest of 1969 and 1970. A few earlier and later items are also included, as well as material from a conference on "Lead poisoning in children" held at the University on 25-26 March 1969.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  The materials in Box 1 were transferred to the Rockefeller University Archives by Dr. Chase as a single group. Received or inventoried 1980 December 23.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted for a period of ten (10) years from the date of gift.
  - Conference material: Lead poisoning in children, Rockefeller University, 25-26 March. 1969. Program, news releases, miscellaneous, 1969 March 25-26 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Manuscripts (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Proposal: "Rockefeller University Student Proposals" Spring 1968; "Comments on Rockefeller University Student Proposal, " by Alfred E. Mirsky and Sonia Wohl, 15 May 1968
    - Talk: "Projections from the Past to the Future (or Present) " by Merrill W. Chase, 1970 June 12
      Scope and Contents note
      Including lists of slides, letter from F. Seitz, and two letters, from and to, David Rockefeller.
  - Notices and Memoranda, 1966-1971, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Official notices and notices from Committee for a Democratic Society.
  - Posters."E Pluribus Sickness" poster, with "Nine Lives Has a Cat". rhyme, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Printed Matter (Box 1)
    - The Newspaper, issued by Committee for a Democratic Society, Rockefeller University
      - Vol. 1 Nos. 1,2,4,5,6, 1968 October-1969 June (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Vol. 2 Nos. 1,2,3,4,5, 1969 October-1970 June (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Vol. 3 No. 1, 1970 November (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - (No vol. nos.) February 1972; May 1972 reprinted from March 1970 issue), 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Other clippings (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Slides: 48 slides showing posters, student marches, 1969 June-1970 September (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Student posters, (oversize) (Package 1)
    Due to the oversize nature and potentially brittle condition of this material, special arrangements may be required in order to view materials. Individual items may be restricted due to preservation concerns.
- 1969-1972, 1 box
  Arrangement
  Box 2 Arranged first by subject, then chronologically.
  Box 2 Received in May, 1980.
  Box 2: Correspondence, minutes, manuscripts, reports, drafts, laboratory notes, clippings and reprints.
  - Allergy Foundation of America. Expert Panel on Diagnostic Criteria for Allergic Disorders. Diseases include asthma and rhinitis, 1970-1972, 1975; 1 inch (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Correspondence, minutes, questionnaires, reprints, notes.
    Subjects: asthma, rhinitis.
  - Enzyme detergents. American Academy of Allergy. Ad Hoc Committee on Enzymes, 1980
    Note by M.W. Chase, 22 May 1980: "The materials here represent the story of the American Academy of Allergy fighting the soap industry's introduction of bacterial proteolytic enzymes into washing powders. The upshot is that the industry withdrew the addition of enzymes".
    - Enzyme Committee files, 1969 October-1971 December 1971 January; 1 inch (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
      Correspondence, drafts of protocols, notes, manuscript of editorial published as "Sensitization to the enzymes in detergents" Lawrence M. Lichtenstein, I. Leonard Bernstein, Francis C. Lowell, Jordan N. Fink, David A. Levy, Solbert Permutt, Raymond G. Slavin, Sidney Les-kowitz, Merrill W. Chase, Jerry Dolovich, Journal of Allergy 47 (January 1971) 53-55. Also includes some correspondence with Federal Trade Commission, New York Academy of Sciences, and Proctor and Gamble.
    - Published magazine and newspaper articles, reports, and manuscripts, 1970 March-1971 November; ½ inch (Box 2, Folder 4)
      Clippings, reprints.
      See, for example, Paul Brodeur, "The Enigmatic Enzyme," The New Yorker, 16 January 1971.
- Slide: "Support the Judicial Committee,: with explanatory letter from Chase, 6 Jan 1981, 1970 1981 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  Correspondence. Photos.
- Reprints
  - M.W. Chase. "Irreverent Recollections from Cooke and Coca 1928-1978" Journal of Allergy and Clinical Immunology 64 (November 1979) 306-320, 1 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Reprint.
  - Merrill W. Chase, editor, Microbiology in New York City, The New York City Branch, The American Society for microbiologists, 1975; 2 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Campus unrest/Judicial Committee, 1970 1972 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  Mimeographed announcements, circular letters, posters, newsletter memoranda, clippings.
  Conditions Governing Access note
  Closed until December 1990.
- "Proposal on Rockefeller University Investment Policy", [1971], undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  [Campus unrest material].
  Announcement of protests, Apr May [1971].
- "Ten Year Scroll, " re scroll presented to Simon Flexner in 1910 (Location of original unknown), 1965 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  Correspondence. Photos. Photograph (B&W) of scroll.
- "The Early Days of the Hospital-by Homer F. Swift - Presented at Staff Rounds, Hospital of the R.I., April 30, 1952." Typescript, 23 pp., with pencil markings by George W. Corner, ca. 1960 and M.W. Chase letter, 18 June 1981 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  Correspondence.
- RI Scientific Staff 1901-1919, graph, 1955, photographic print (Box 2, Folder 11)
  Handwritten description of graph by M.W. Chase of photo. "Constructed in 1955 by from STUDIES 10, vii, viii (1910) other records, with discrepancies eliminated by Hazel Olmstead, Secretary to Edric Smith Business Manager, who searched old records in vault of R.I.M.R.".
  Photos. Photographic prints of graph; also 4x5 negative of graph.
- "Early Scientific Staff, Department of the Laboratories, 1906-1911 (RIMR) ". Table, 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- "Extramural scientific workers supported by RIMR, 1901-1910" (Box 2, Folder 12)
  Source: "Studies of The Rockefeller Institute 10, ix, x, xi (1910)". (List of names).
- "Division of The Hospital: Early Years, 1910 - 1914". Table (Box 2, Folder 12)
- "The Princeton Branch of R.I.M.R" (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Department of Animal Pathology, 1915-1930
  - Department of Animal & Plant Pathology, 1931-1950; 2 pp. typescript
- "Division of Animal Pathology, Early 1914-1927 Scientific Staff, 1914-1927" (Box 2, Folder 13)
  Listed in order of appointments only Graph.
- "Staff Meetings", 1 typescript page (Box 2, Folder 14)
- "Synopsis, Early Bronkian Years". 2 page photocopied typescript, 1954-1964 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Leonhard Wachsmuth/Members of The Faculty Club, 29 May 1981, on his retirement as bartender of The Faculty Club, 3 pp. photocopied typescript (Box 2, Folder 14)
- "A Bouquet for Mabel Bright." On the Occasion of a Luncheon in Her Honor. The Rockefeller University, 1968 November 27 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  Booklet and covering letter, Detlev W. Bronk/M.W. Chase, December 1969.
- Photocopies (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Peyton Rous, "Hail to the Greatly Fortunate, " The Rockefeller University Review, 1967 May-June
  - D.W. Bronk/M.W. Chase, re anniversary dinner and table assignments, 1968
  - Table assignments, Dinner for Long-Service employees, 1969
  - Table assignments, Anniversary/Retirement dinner, 1970-1972
  - Invitation to Buffet Dinner Dance to celebrate the Twentieth Anniversary of the Faculty and Students Club, 1978 May 12
- American Society for Microbiology, ASM News 47 (June 1981)
  Separated Materials
  This file was removed from the M.W. Chase papers and inserted into the Theobald Smith papers. See Archivist for assistance.
  See: Dolman, "Theobald Smith and His Presidential Address to the Society of American Bacteriologists [1903]" pp. 231-235. [added to Theobald Smith file archives].
- Armed Forces Epidemiological Board (AFEB), 1958-1960 (Box 3, Folder 1, Folder 2)
  Correspondence. Includes:.
  "Minutes of the Special Session on Radiation. Effects on Infection and Immunity." Duplicated typescript, 7 pp.
  "Progress report, December 1958, on properidin, with Chase/D.M. Pillsbury, 16 Feb 1959, comments. Chase holograph notes of annual meeting, 24, 25 Mar 1959, Commission on Immunization.
  "Annual Report of the Commission on Cutaneous Diseases of the AFEB, 1 May 1959-30 Apr 1960," with attached reports of Investigators Harvey Blank, Herman N. Eisen, Abraham G. Osler, Thomas H. Sternberg and Earl G. McNall, Donald M. Pillsbury.
- St. Jude Hospital (Memphis, Tenn.) [Scientific Advisory Board], 1962
  - General correspondence, 1962-1964 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Correspondence. primarily with Donald F. Pinkel.
  - Hiramoto, Raymond, 1962-1964 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Correspondence. includes grant applications.
  - Slotnick, Irving J., 1963 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Grant application.
  - Duplicated material, 1962-1964 (Box 3, Folder 6-7)
    Includes memoranda, reports and report drafts, minutes of meetings.
- "Progress Report to the Scientific Advisory Board, March 1964" (Box 3, Folder 8)
- M.W. Chase notes (Box 3, Folder 9)
  Includes notes on Scientific Advisory Board meetings by investigators at St. Jude Hospital.
- Reprints (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Pharmacopoeia (I), 1946-1948 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  Correspondents include: Daniel Borgen, Arthur Cherkin, r.k. Richards barren M. Cox, Jr., Howard C. Hopps, Robert A. Harte.
  Chase/Daniel Borgen, 4 Dec 1947, "I am writing to you as co-chairman of a subcommittee on Antigenicity having to do with Protein Hydrolysate Injection under the auspices Df U.S.P. Revision Committee...".
  "A.D.M.A.-A.P.M.A. Subcommittee on Amino Acids. Report to U.S.P. Amino Acids Advisory Committee" 20 Nov 1947, Philadelphia, PA.
  "Fourth draft. Antigenicity, tentative standard for." 1 p., undated.
  Robert C. Anderson et al., "Some Pharmacologic Tests on 'Supprotein' (Protein Hydrolysate, Lilly), 6%." 6 pp., typescript carbon, undated.
  R.A. Harte/Chase, 6 Nov 1946, enc "copies of excerpts of previous bulletins and memoranda from Dr. Cook's Office" re antigenicity tests for protein hydrolysate preparation.
- Pharmacopoeia. (II)
  - 1946-1947 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    Correspondents include Robert A. Harte, Arthur Cherkin, Charles F. Kade, Jr., Melville Sahyun, H.B. Devlin, R.A. Brown, E.M. Nelson, E. Fullerton Cook.
    Correspondence. E. Fullerton Cook/Chase, 18 Oct 1946, inviting Chase to assis in drafting of an "Antigenicity of Protein Hydrolysate Injection" for Committee of Revision of the Pharmacopoeia of the United State of America 1940-1950.
  - 1947 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    Correspondents include K.K. Chen K.S. Pilcher, Howard C. Hopps, George W. Thorn, Warren M. Cox, Jr.
    Correspondence. Chase/George Thorn, 12 Jun 1947 re anaphylaxis tests and Thorn remarks at the "Conference at Philadelphia in February".
- Pharmacopoeia (III), 1947 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  Correspondents include Arthur Cherkin, L.W. Roth, D.V. Frost, R.K. Richards, Warren M. Cox, Jr.
- Minutes of meetings and other duplicated material of the U.S.P. Amino Acids Advisory Committee, 1947-1948 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  Drafts of Chase memorandum on "Antigenicity of Protein Hydrolysate Injection".
  Technical data and reports.
- René Dubos, Holograph manuscript review of Resistance to Tuberculosis: Experimental Studies in Native and Acquired Defensive Mechanisms, by Max B. Lurie (Harvard University Press, 1965). Review published in American Review of Respiratory Diseases 92 (1965) 500-1. Photocopy of review added to folder. [This manuscript was given to Dr. Chase's wife by Dr. Clara Lynch before Dr. Lynch] (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Reprints (Box 4)
  - F.R. Sabin et al., "A study of the toxic properties of tuberculoproteins and polysaccharides, " J. Exp. Med. 53 (1 Jan 1931) 51-80 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - K.C. Smithburn, "The standardization of longevity against dose in experimental tuberculosis...," J. Exp. Med. 64 (1 Nov 1936) 771-790 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - K.C. Smithburn, "Virulence of bovine tubercule bacilli"; K.C. Smithburn, "Histopathology of experimental tuberculosis", K.C. Smith-burn et al., "Haematological studies..". Amer. Rev. Tuberc. 36 (Nov 1937) 637-691 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - F.R. Sabin et al., "Cellular reactions to polysaccharides from tubercule bacilli..". J. Exp. Med. 68 (1 Oct 1938) 563-582 / F.R. Sabin and A.L. Joyner, "Tubercular allergy without infection," J. Exp. Med. 68 (1 Nov 1938) 659-676 /K.C. Smith-burn and F.R. Sabin, "Reactions of normal and tuberculous animals..". J. Exp. Med. 68 (1 Nov 1938) 641-658. [The last two reprints have markings] (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - A. Claude and J.B. Murphy, "Transmissible tumors of the fowl," Physiol. Revs. 13 (Apr 1933) 246-275 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - A. Claude, "Properties of the causative agent of a chicken tumor. X and XI". J. Exp. Med. 61 (1 Jan 1935) 27-40, 41-57 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - A. Claude and A. Rothen, ibid. XII..". Amer. J. Cancer, 26 (Feb 1936) 344-350 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - A. Claude, "A Fraction from normal chicken embryo..". Proc. Soc. Exp. Biol. Med. 39 (1938) 398-403 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Manuscripts, (typescript copies) (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - "Presentation of Robert Barry Bloom for the Degree of Ph. D. June 12, 1963 (Final version for 4. 5 minute presentation). Merrill W. Chase", a
  - "Transfer Factor and the Chase Laboratory." [Merrill W. Chase, 1982], b
  - "The Immunological Enigma of Transfer Factor. Merrill W. Chase", [1982]; c
  - M.W. Chase/C. Kopp, 22 Nov 1983 re 1st Transfer Factor Workshop 1973; includes Christmas/holiday cards, d
- Christmas/holiday cards (Box 4, Folder 4)
  Received 1984 January 10. Additions 1984 July 27.
  - Cards from Esther Cohn (mother of Zanvil Cohn)
  - P.J. Dragsted family (of R Dubos lab)
  - Alfred and Sonia Mirsky
  - Hal Simon family (of R. Dubos laboratory)
  - Norman and Esther Stoll
  - Ian Smith family (Dubos lab)
- Historical Slides of R.I.M.R, 3 boxes of slides (Box 5)
  "Slides made for M.W. Chase in 1955, and slides used by Dr. Homer F. Swift at a Hospital Staff Rounds; among the Swift slides are some which clearly were made for his lecture with his name, and others which were probably made a long time previously and perhaps used by him in some prior talk."--Merrill W. Chase, 1982 June 24
  - untitled, one slide box 3¼ × 4-in. (Box 5, Box 1)
    Negatives used: 191, 193, 247, 279, 280, 2201, 3341-7, 5571-7, 5856, 5989.
    Probably mew negatives from large forms negatives contact prints: 16563, 16566, B-25396.
    - Schermerhorn House, H.F. Swift, 1952 April 15; 3346-7; carton
    - The "Rock" with Schermerhorn House M.W. Chase, 1955 April 28; 5571-7
    - Building of R.I. Hospital
      - Glacial scars, 1908 November 18; 193
      - Early construction, 1908 November 4; 191
      - Working on the cliff, 64th Street M.W. Chase, 1955 May 5; 16563
      - Hospital excavation & Seaview Sanatorium, 1909 January 11; 247
      - Working on cliff, 64th Street M.W. Chase., 1955 May 5; 16566
      - Steelwork of Hospital, 1909 April 13; 279
      - Steelwork completes, 1909 June 11; 280
      - Groundfloor plan of Hospital, 2201
      - Completion of Hospital M.W. Chase, 1955 May 5
        (Probably reduced from large glass plate via copy negative without recording plate number).
    - Inside Isolation Building
      - Interior view, B-25396
    - War Demonstration Hospital
      - Winter view M.W. Chase, 7130
      - Interior M.W. Chase, 5989
      - Winter view from Hospital roof, 5856
        Turn over-mounted backwards.
  - untitled, one slide box 3¼ × 4-in. (Box 5, Box 2)
    Negatives used: 1023-76, 1760, 2090, 2377, 2519, 2701, 2702/03, 4055, 4062, 4063, 5542-7, 5567-7, 8521-A, 8855.
    Probably seconding negatives: 10490, 12207, 12208, A-25396.
    - Early Groups and Individuals, R.I. Hospital, carton
      - Rufus Cole, 12207
      - Isolation ward, A-25396
      - First Staff, 1910-1911; 4055
      - Staff May, 1916; 4063
      - Staff, 1916-1917; 4062
      - 1914 July 2, 2519
      - 1920 April 1, 8521-A
      - Rufus Cole at bedside, 12208
      - 1921 May 5, 10490
    - Simon Flexner
      - S.F. at desk H.F. Swift, 1952 April 21; 1023-76
      - S.F. at microscope
      - First rented "twin building", 1913 May 14; 2A90
    - Ten-year Scroll honoring S.F.
      - Part I, 2701
      - Part II, 1913 October 26; 2702
    - Exteriors 1906, 1916, both from East River (1/9/1913=1760), 2377, 1760
      - View from Avenue A.M.W. Chase, 1916; 8855
      - Main Building, North Laboratory nearing completion MWC "15-6"
      - Aerial view (probably after 1929), 1955 April 28; MWC 5542-7
      - Aerial view from the East MWC, 1955 May 5; 5567-7
  - untitled, one slide box 3¼ × 4-in. (Box 5, Box 3)
    Negatives used: 6, 7, 189, 201, 2439, 4058, 4069, 5568-7, 5638-7A, 5638-7B, 13141, 13142, 13143, 13146.
    13 some special numbering system, not before 1924.
    - Main Building, 1906 (Box 5, Box 3)
      - Floor plan second floor Chase, 1955 May 25
        Negatives used: 5638-7A
      - Floor plan third floor Chase, 1955 May 25
        Negatives used: 5638-7B
      - Laboratory (before 1906?) Chase
        Negatives used: 6
      - Media room Chase, 1955 May 25
        Negatives used: 201
      - Early worker (Gates?) Chase, 1955 May 5
        Negatives used: 199
      - Room 314 (Main Building evidently) Chase
        Negatives used: 4065
      - Cleaning room (mounted in reverse)
        Negatives used: 7
    - First Board Meeting of Scientific Directors (Box 5, Box 3)
      Negatives used: 4058
    - Alexis Carrel operating Chase (Box 5, Box 3)
      Negatives used: 2439
    - Dog runs, East side of middle animal building, top floor 13 Some specimen (ca. 1920?) numbering, circa 1920? (Box 5, Box 3)
    - Chart of growth in Staff members, by M.W. Chase, 1955 April 28 (Box 5, Box 3)
      Negatives used: 5568-7.
    - Exhibits in Alsace-Lorraine, 1923 Chase, 1955 May 5 (Box 5, Box 3)
      Negatives used: 13141, 13142, 13143, 13146.
- Chart in cover: "Ammonium sulfate concentration conversion tables" copy made by John D. Gregory, of original used in Moses Kunitz lab, circa 1950; Legal 5inch Hollinger box (Box 6, Folder 1)
  Received 1984 February 8.
- 63rd St. Subway, Legal 5-inch Hollinger box
  - Correspondence, circa 1976-1977; Legal 5inch Hollinger box (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Clippings, Legal 5inch Hollinger box (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Maps, Legal 5inch Hollinger box (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Photos, Legal 5inch Hollinger box (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Memos, announcements, position papers, etc., Legal 5inch Hollinger box (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Final supplemental Environmental Impact Statement. East 63rd Street Line, Boroughs of Manhattan and Queens, UMTA Project No. NY-03-0045. US Department Transportation, Urban Mass Transportation Administration, 1978 April; 2 paper volumes (Box 6)
- Annual Dinner for Retirees and attainment of long-term services at the University., 1973-1979; 4 sheets of foamcore board. (Package 2)
  83 pictures taken by Merrill W. Chase or his wife Cynthia, in the years 1973, 1974, 1975, 1976 and 1979 at the Annual Dinner for Retirees.
  Also included are six color-coded lists which identify the persons shown.
  Presented to the RU archives by Merrill W. Chase, June 9, 1981.